okay welcome back everyone we are here
in part one of the workshop that John
clippinger and our partners at first
principal first are coordinating so with
that for
the next session please John to you and
take it
away well thank you very much um I would
like to just to share a a deck with the
the group here if I could um and uh and
provide a sort of an overview of of um
what we'll be talking about in this
particular session can you see that now
is this is this good for
you okay great um and we'll be
anticipating with Andrew is uh sure will
be coming on and providing the tutorial
but what I would like to do is in in the
first inst of the is is being able to
provide an overview of why active
inference uh is important why active
inference agents this whole perspective
that we're taking here is worth people's
attention and pay uh and being concerned
about um and what it has to offer to
address some of the the the the
limitations of the current uh AI systems
for example large language models and
some of the uh agenda architectures have
come out of them um and and in that in
that context what I looking at is said
what is the current state of large
language models and and agent uh an
agents and I think you there's a lot of
activity that's been talked about but
there there's still no Mission critical
applications yet there's a lot of an
exploration you have people like um
Salesforce developing Little Einstein
that can do uh various kinds of uh
workflow automation you have co-pilot
and Microsoft but it's not it's not it's
not really core critical not to say that
it won't be but it it is still uh is
still on the experimental phase it's
still a back box we do not know real lot
how it works hence you have issues of
data Pro Providence you have a question
of how to govern it um and there's more
recently there's a concern about you've
invested a trillion dollar but there's
an unknown business model coming out so
there's a lot of money that's going into
it but it's not clear that the current
framing of uh of uh AI um as it's now
known is really is going to be viable
and part of the issue here is is that we
and I love this example from The New
Yorker is like who's modeling who we're
actually putting data into the models
we're trying to write representations
and we have that interaction but there's
not necessarily an abstraction that's
coming out so it's this is kind of this
uh relationship of of seeing ourselves
mirroring ourselves and going and this
sort of cycle um and what we have now is
a certain hype cycle so it's around the
peak of the this is 2023 from the uh
Gartner group and it's the generative AI
is at the top of the hype hype cycle and
then if it's hard to read this
particular uh graph but you'll see that
principle AI is is U basically um on the
early cycle it's on the early phase of
it but it's not seen as taking very long
where some like uh you're going to
have AGI is seen as being like 20 years
out it's the top of the hyp cycle I
think if we update this there's now I
think it's starting to be appreciated
that the generative models and the
expectations and the kind of problems
and the cost associated with them and
the lack of improvement the the the lack
of degree of improvement through
successive models is starting to show
through so the the Next Generation open
AI shift strategy is a rate of GPI
improveing slow in other words the new
Orion model is not did not have the
level of improvements that they were
expecting I think that is something to
take an account um and hence the cost of
of of training and inferencing is
extremely high and and with that the the
M the fact that you have this enormous
consumption of energy uh that Microsoft
is going to have to recommission Three
Mile Island and drive one of their own
data centers this shows that the Imp
practicality of having to um have so
much
computation um in order to have work and
make these models work and I I think
that this is starting to be recognized
within the the the limitations of large
language models and sort of the the the
parametric approach to to uh modeling uh
AI modeling and I think just to start to
step into what what we have now what
we're looking at I I love this is
another a cartoon from the the New
Yorker and since says to think it all
began with letting autocomplete
finishing our sentences and well
autocomplete is a sort of for Markoff
chain so we are we are having the sort
of chains on top of chains that we've
been able to to develop some pretty rich
representations of of of human uh
activity text and actually forms of
cognition but there's not an underlying
model there and so what we're looking at
there may be some foundational issues
that are coming up in in very large
language models and that the fact that
it is a black box is not explicable uh
it locks internal causal models um
there's not a way of reducing the
complexity it's sort of a batch
processing there's no real-time updating
and that batch processing we seem is
extremely expensive and and so we we
we're caught on on on that that issue um
it's not atic it has no no no means of a
spontaneous adaptation and correction on
its own um and suddenly doesn't know
what it it doesn't know that has no way
of representing its completeness of its
knowledge and and adapting coherently to
that and and and also I would say it's
not it's not derived from sort of
fundamental scientific principles it's
really sort of an engineering phenomena
on a case-by casee base uh basis now
this is changing um and I think the same
issue if you start to see foundational
issues for multi-agent uh llms in other
words the transition to to making
agentic architectures where you can um
create a particular agent that's
optimized to do a particular task or
role a lot of the success of that agent
is depending on the quality of the
prompts of that and sometimes those
prompts are good sometimes the prompts
are bad but there's not a really
principled way of doing that currently
and so they have a very fixed way of of
of and specialized kind of goals it's
sort of a a a mechanical it's it's so
the instantiation of an industrial model
um that we see um now what we we rather
than having a a a sort of biological
self-correcting model it is s of these
fixed static models now what I would say
the active inference difference here um
is is that it's really developed from
first principles and I think and and I
think you're going to see the Andrew is
going to go into this much more detail
but it really C it cuts across different
disciplines that themselves have been
uring fairly quickly in the last two or
three decades and so it is going in
basic basic physics Quantum information
Theory the a whole idea of computational
Science Biology and cognitive science
all these are intersecting into creating
a new way of looking at what
intelligence and life are and how
they're
interconnected um and it also builds in
wellestablished statistical methods
including Markoff blankets blazi and
belief mod the stff the work has been
done with JD a pearl um and basically
what you at active infine does and and
just to highlight is it codifies a
predictive brain thesis that's been
nurturing in in neuroscience and so the
pr and then that in turn sort of mimics
the processes of the scientific method
and when I get so we think about what
the method is that you're you're trying
to codify and and I turn to Richard
Fan's comment well quoted comment that I
can't what I can't create I can't
understand so there's a new kind of
criteria for what it means to have a um
to understand something is be able to
model to create a digital twin if I can
recreate something then I understand
what it is and if I can replicate that
behavior and that that's sort of the the
the principles that you find in active
inference from the very beginning is ah
how do I grant a generative model how
does a living agent have a generative
model of it s in its world and this this
really owes it work his Origins back to
to uh the work that's done with J Pearl
on his understanding in causal reasoning
and also markof blankets you how does
some what is an autonomous thing and
this is where Carl fritzen anal work how
how does something maintain its
separation from the world in which it is
in and so it is not governed by that
things but maintains its autonomy and
there's a certain kind of topology there
that and something has certain kinds of
inter internal States it has external
States Observer States and action States
and there so there's a lot of deep
Concepts that's in it I'm sure Andrew
will go into that much more detail um
and then what we have is is the active
invers agents themselves as sentient
live things so you're creating something
and there very different than say a
large language model you're taking
something it has agency and it has a
representation of itself in the context
in which is trying to stay alive um and
so it's self-organizing it's
self-healing is self-replicating and
symbiotic in the sense that it evolves
complexity Mutual synchrony with other
living things in its World in its Niche
it's a joint Niche construction uh hence
sentience is is sort of a is a kind of
situational intelligence an awareness
that's granted in the survival of that
particular agent and the person that's
sort of the the context of the person
who's really behind this is Carl priston
and and um my own experience of being
someone who is very interested in sort
of and artificial intelligence from from
many many years ago and
self-organizing systems as cybernetics
it really hasn't been until the last
five or six 10 years that this has come
together in a coherent uh not only
coherent Theory but a whole coherent
formalism um and through what what car
would call physics of living things and
he's one of the most SED sists in the
world it's a neurosci is has done um
basically developed a reputation
neuroimaging and infer the structure
from the brain from Neuro Imaging uh and
he applied the free energy principle
which we'll go into more discussion to
later um and so one of the I love this
idea of a tree foil knot it's sort of
like okay is it is sort of this
autocatalytic biotic system it's really
important it's a living system and it
has certain kinds of characteristics
that are all interwined with itself one
cycle synchronizes is exception or it's
a representation external world to
minimize uncertainty the other does it
internally it has to align that with the
external world and then you have another
cycle that has expected free energy
minimization it makes predictions about
how to change itself in its World um and
so what we have here is basically a a a
what I think active iners offers is a
really a soundness of grounding in bi in
biology and physics and so you have a
sort of a ground truth of evidence space
that do I make predictions and do those
predictions allow me to act and survive
in the world um so it can be explicit it
can be explainable and and we'll see
we'll talk about this later but you can
have since it has cause of models and
language and knowledge graphs it can
explain why it doing what is doing and
also it can talk about explain why how
much it doesn't there degrees of
uncertainty associated with it and
there's also the potential of self-
policing self cor acting mechanism and I
think this this is really important in
other words you can design a active
inference agent to to live with in
certain constraints and Bounds and you
can build in certain me me mechanisms
that have for self-governance that
cannot be captured uh so it's actions
are within the limits of its designed
Mission and not to have generate
negative externalities so this I will
sort of leave with this one and then
just to quote William Blake I mean who
talks about this
a poetic form is a fractal nature
reality see the world in a grain of sand
and heaven and a wildflower and hold
Infinity in the palm of your hand and
turny an hour this just sort of pulls it
together in a more poetic sense so on
this I would hope to uh hand off to uh
to uh Andrew if
uh thank
you I
great thanks John
um and so hi everyone I'm me Andrew um
Andrew pase I'm uh currently involved
with the active inference Institute it's
been great partnering with with uh Dr
clippinger with the director of The
Institute you know we've we've been
doing some really exciting work lately
um and I want to address a lot of the
points that that John has made although
most of that will come tomorrow when we
give some major updates on our biofirm
so today in the spirit of like an
initial workshop and kind of
introduction to active inference I'm
actually going to refer back to this
tutorial that I gave a couple months ago
uh at a International Conference for
computational social science meaning
folks who were involved in sociology
economics uh you know a broad range of
fields and uh the context was applying
active inference a lot of these
principles that John is referring to to
social science research
uh and and I I basically make the the
claim and the argument this is already
being done so I'm not necessarily
providing a bunch of new information but
it's just to kind of extend the dialogue
to computational social scientists like
here's how we can apply active inference
to you know your particular setting in
different ways so uh we'll just kind of
cover some of of what I went over and
you know I apologize if there's any
Whiplash from how quickly I go through
these slides um but we're just going to
move a little quickly um so the cont
context again of this this uh this
tutorial that I gave was it was split
into three parts it was a 3.5 hour
Workshop where we actually we started
with talking about agent based modeling
you know how it's traditionally been
done and then followed by that something
that I would call a cognitive turn in
agent based modeling that's happened
over the past couple decades as you know
there are these kind of calls for you
know we have the computational resources
now we have an immense amount more of
you know Empirical research and
validation of different kinds of
principles related to human cognition
coming from Neuroscience
neurobiology uh you know cognitive
modeling uh studies of neuronal Dynamics
uh organisms in their environment all
those kind of things so so there's a
shift to that and then uh the most
recent you know means of trying to
establish that the broader
state-ofthe-art
area is uh using reinforcement learning
agents so we'll touch on what those are
uh and kind of how that work works and
you know anyone who's kind of been
looking at the the agentic uh framework
for for what's being done today they'll
probably already be familiar with
reinforcement learning then after that
we'll go into active inference and how
that kind of kind of bridges together a
lot of these different things um and
apologies I want to just mention real
quick uh you can actually go to this
this link uh the quickest way of
following that is just by going to
Google type you know my name Andrew pase
and then you could type GitHub or ic2 S2
in any case you'll come up to uh the
landing page for this you'll see links
to all previous slides I've made uh
slides that I'm making for tomorrow uh
I'm also making a lot of his Open Access
uh so so there's code that people can
you know play around with and things
like that um so agent-based modeling uh
this has been done you know this goes
back to roughly 70s 80s with a lot of
you know uh initial developments of
computer technology and being able to
realize that oh we can we can simulate
uh people right in some loose sense in
in some kind of simplistic sense uh how
can we simulate people and why would we
want to do that we would want to do that
so that we could maybe imagine uh
hypothetical scenarios imagine you're
designing some kind of policy or want to
test a policy uh and see you know oh if
I recreate that in a simulation and have
people in the environment where I'm
implementing that policy uh what happens
what's the collective outcome you know
what occurs so all kinds of fascinating
work from uh shelling and the the
traditional way of looking at uh housing
segregation for example th handling
those kinds of problems where do people
land where how do they settle you know
in in in uh like a residential
environment uh even more interesting
work later after that Santa Fe Institute
creating an artificial stock market uh
where you where you have agents who are
basically interacting with this kind of
financial environment where they're
looking at stock prices changing they
make choices to you know buy or sell Etc
and see how that plays out Recreation of
housing booms and busts excuse me not
housing Financial so this can be applied
in many different ways point and so what
what is agent-based modeling you know in
its fundamental
principles and how does that relate back
to active inference which we'll get to
um key components of agent based
modeling is that we have agents kind of
the catch word of the day um
traditionally agents are you know that
they just represent some entity a living
organism you know this this can be used
for for biological and Zoological
studies trying to understand you know
how ants or or insects you know
interacted environment or at a broader
scale how humans and entire you know
societies and cultures might interact
with their
environment and and so what's really
important about this with agents
environments simulations is that know we
just kind of run a simulation over a
series of time steps what and so we let
Dynamics play out and then what is it
that that composes those Dynamics it's
the assumptions we make about agents
what is their behavior what do we think
that they do you know how do we program
them in this way or in that way uh and
then also what are the aspects or
characteristics of the environment you
know and so again given that a lot of
this work was done starting in the 80s
going forward with with with very you
know we nearly archaic at this point uh
forms of like computational resources
it's like things were kept as simple as
as possible and there are a variety of
guidelines that need to be used to
develop agent-based models for running
these kinds of simulations uh you know
and so so some of them even running up
to to 2007 here this is the work of of
doctors laser and fredman who are
respectively uh have been involved with
Northeastern University in Stanford um
you know that they give some guidelines
for how to do this um guideline one and
two uh in some is you need realistic uh
assumptions that you're making about
your agents but not too realistic in the
sense that they're too complex one
because we don't have computers that are
Advanced enough to run highly
sophisticated complex agents and then
also you know if we make if we make too
many assumptions then the situation
won't generalize well you might be
making an agent based model for one very
very particular scenario where it it's
not adaptable across different real
world circumstances right so we need
some kind of balance in terms of the
complexity of the assumptions we're
making the Simplicity of the assumptions
we're
making the rest are a bit more plain
which are one uh reproducibility you
should publish your code you should
document it very well other researchers
should be able to kind of take up the
torch and be able to experiment with
your code um you know we at the Active
inference Institute we're constantly
putting out new get Hub repositories and
documenting or processes so that other
people can come get involved so I just
you know want to mention that there's a
big problem in reproducibility in
science today and it's very well known
you know so uh just wanted to touch on
that the nont reality it's like why do
agent-based modeling uh if it doesn't
help us uncover anything you know why
why not just sit down and have a
conversation about you know what what do
we expect to happen what are our
thoughts about what's going to happen
why you know do all of this um with with
setting up these programs and and agent
based models and designing them if we
can just come up to the same conclusions
through speaking so you you want your
results to be interesting you want to
make realistic assumptions that you know
we can kind of have all these things
synthesize um together so I made some
points about balancing Simplicity and
complexity this is just a representation
of uh you know this these These are
common problems in machine learning and
deep learning you know you you go and
get uh you know University education
these are the core components of all of
your courses you know this isn't
specific to active inference like wide
ranging you know concern how do you uh
create a model that is realistic enough
capture uh and and explain the en the
phenomena you're looking at um but uh
simple enough to where it's adaptable to
different circumstances you know there
you know these are kind of in part uh
you know just as uh Dr clippinger
referred to Richard feeman you know I
just some reminders from you know famous
statistician George GP box you know all
mod all models are wrong but some models
are useful right we're always trying to
approximate a reality and so the
question is how do we come CL closer to
approximating uh our reality and
so how do we actually you know using
modern computational resources using all
these new advances in all these fields
how do we actually make you know new
forms of what we'll call cognitive
agents who exhibit the kind of mental
Dynamics and social dynamics between
them that actually better approximate
real human
behavior so I give some definitions the
differences between traditional agent
based models and what agent assumptions
are are being made and uh more often
than not for the sake of Simplicity an
agent is pretty one-dimensional if they
observe X then they do y otherwise they
do see these very simple pre-program
roles they're not autonomous they're
they're kind of like you can think of
them as like thermostats or something
like that right the temperature is too
high you you turn it down if it's too
low you turn it up um that kind of
reactive framework uh there's no beliefs
about what's going on there's no
internal goals per se aside from a
single homeostat that is you know
maintain the temperature at what you
said um cognitive ages however the
expectation for those this throughout
the the recent uh agent-based modeling
literature is like how do we achieve
cognitive ages we exhibit internal
cognitive mechanisms they exhibit
perception action they actually learn
and update their models I'll make a
point that you know as John referenced
with in the case of llms which I'll
cover much more deeply tomorrow llms do
not I mean it's so expensive to train
them and you you typically just train
them once right and so um they don't
learn in real time they're kind of stuck
with the knowledge that they have they
have a lot of it to be fair they've been
trained on you know thousands thousands
thousands of documents uh and so on um
but but that's it like that's you have
and then and then we have to figure out
how to work with LMS from there with
cognitive active inference agents as
well as other kinds of cognitive agents
the ideas that they can learn in real
time meaning in the moment and adjust
their expectations their beliefs to
what's actually going on now um and then
also planning so the capacity for being
able to infer or guess using evidence
that they take in like what's going to
happen in the future right and that's
immensely important in today's climate
right where we're that I mean that's in
part the reason we're doing in face
model is to attempt to plan to test
things to to come up with our own
inference about what's going to happen
in the future and then act in actionable
ways to to realize our own goals in the
future right so that's that's you know
ideally that's what an agent would do
and be capable of um and then with you
know this cognitive turn we we're also
looking at a broad synthesis of all
these fields you know as John mentioned
we're looking at things like cybernetics
and machine learning we're looking at
physics information Theory um people are
starting to it's great it's it's
fascinating that so many uh
interdisciplinary conversations can come
up and collaborations between
researchers of various backgrounds
because it's like oh you know once we
once we realize what it is we're trying
to do here we can start to pull from
maybe principles or relate principles
from other fields to this field what
works what makes sense what's
empirically you know what can be
validated so on so it's it's um you know
it's a very rich field right now and
then furthermore a lot of traditional
agent based modeling has been done using
uh uh software called net logo which is
very specific uh it's it's good if you
want to do agent based modeling like you
just learned this one programming
language there's a GUI like an interface
for using it highly simplistic it is not
integratable with other tools not
integratable with you know llms with
natural language all those kinds of
things um and it's so it's it's very
narrow you know it's good at what it
does uh with cognitive agents we would
want to be able to pull from all kinds
of other resources that are you know
available including open source ones uh
being able to use apis being able to
pull in other kinds of real world data
not just purely simulations you know so
um there's just a lot of richness behind
this idea of moving to cognitive agents
then there's some basic you know uh
ideas of what makes a cognitive agent
again perception they take in
observations and they infer what's going
on in the world and kind of like we what
we do my stomach growls and I infer that
I'm hungry for it's a very simplistic
example um and then agents are are
generative the sense that they actually
come up with uh their own plans or a you
know choices of what actions to take
based upon what they believe such as I
observe my stomach is growling I iner
I'm hungry I will now choose to go eat
food as like an affordance that's
available to me in my environment so
this is a new way in a certain sense of
doing agent based modeling where before
we were looking at modeling an
environment with a bunch of
one-dimensional Agents you know
predictable agents on the inside if they
see X and they do y otherwise they do Z
but now we have models in a model in the
sense that we're actually able to
internally inspect our ages right by
having this beliefs based frame
framework where agents observe real data
or information and then infer beliefs
about it we're able to then
retroactively look inside the agent and
see what its beliefs are as opposed to
these kind of you know very difficult to
to interpret uh blackbox models that we
find very commonly in deep learning and
and and you know very very highly
performative yet very uh uh difficult to
interpret like neural networks and
architectures like that with with uh
agents we would want to be able to see
in a in almost like a human sense like
what are their beliefs that they're
holding and why are they doing what
they're doing so we need to be able to
accomplish that in order to actually
realize all the additional benefit of
doing this which is being able to look
at you know internal cognition what are
agents learning whenever I whenever I
Implement a new policy or something
right I want to be able to know what's
going on with them internally I want to
know the full impact of of what it is
you know this plan I I'm considering
like
actualizing so let's bring it back um
you know how how do we address all these
traditional criteria how do we make
realistic assumptions how do we um you
know how do we make our code
reproducible that's an easy one because
like well we're still coding the whole
time uh and then you know how do we how
do we derive useful insights from this
um and what are other problems that are
going on like now that we're getting
into cognitive architectures
um and and we we are starting to brush
up against the potential of recreating
more blackbox models right we need to
keep things simple enough like how how
do we navigate all this a common problem
in in social science research and
general but also in data science machine
learning and those kinds of fields uh
reinforcement learning common issue is
what is h how do we handle What's called
the explore exploit tradeoff this is
this is famously an issue uh if you
have't agent who comes up with a
suboptimal uh solution to a problem you
know let's say an agent who's you know
they're trying to figure something out
they find something that they deem to be
good they get a positive you know reward
signal or positive feedback from that
but it's suboptimal there there's
actually a better solution exists they
just don't know about it yet how do you
get an agent to actually be willing to
explore same thing for humans right we
we don't always stick with the you know
the first decent looking you know option
available to us sometimes we we explore
in the sense that we seek better
solutions to problems and this is
especially important and something to be
addressed in agentic Frameworks where if
you're trying to use agents for say
software application or use case like
you want them to be able to find better
Solutions ideally you know at any given
moment especially in a changing context
that might call going forward for better
Solutions you know say agents who were
maintaining an environment that's
subject to uh natural disaster or or or
or climate change right like that that
might call for a whole new set of of of
policies or actions that need to be
taken uh you know that that couldn't be
relied upon in the past so we need
agents who seek new
information um unfortunately in
reinforcement learning you know that
this is still an issue um people are
trying to figure out how to kind of
manually Define
what what defines exploratory behavior
and it tends to boil down to kind of
simple mathematic of of defining like
okay well we'll s we'll we'll modify
these agents so that 90% of the time
they go with the best solution they have
they know about and then 10% of the time
they'll just pick something random that
way they're at least exploring 10% of
the time you know you could put it that
way active inference again I'm sorry I'm
kind of zooming through a lot of this
call this is over three hour tutorial um
but uh rein with active inference ages
this kind of gets naturally naturally
resolved in terms of What's called the
free energy principle which we'll be
getting into um but basically the idea
is if you're able to to have agents who
naturally seek information perhaps in
line with how we do right that when they
come up against something they see oh
there's value in seeking new information
to find even better Solutions the ones I
already have and being able to to do
that in a way that isn't some kind of ad
hoc rule of you know the 90% versus 10%
as I mentioned that's that's um kind of
a key component you know a key
consideration designing agents um so
this brings us to the active active
inference which I I describe here as a
framework for doing agent-based modeling
it uh begins with the free energy
principle uh that I I'll make a lot of
mentions to this nice textbook that
Thomas par Carl friston and you know
their other co-authors published a
couple of years ago um but you know
there perhaps even some more updates to
be made because it's such a lively field
but uh that textbook really lays out a
lot of the core principles and and ways
of getting started with active inference
um the the free energy principle
everything that changes in the brain
must minimize free free energy now
despite all of this energy disciplinary
communication dialogue between you know
again cybernetics with psychology with
behavioral economics um that actually
sounds quite simple right to be able to
boil everything down to oh we have a
brain it's trying to minimize free
energy that that that almost sounds
simple enough to where we might be able
to employ that as a kind of you know
simple assumption that we make an agent
based modeling it's
quantifiable uh it's it's a
presume Pres assumed is the wrong word
uh but but something like a principle
that can be applied in any given
circumstance whenever we're looking at
you know the these organisms who are
self-organizing such as humans such as
you know living organisms such as you
know plants in an environment that's
being taken care of uh you know that
they exhibit this this kind of uh
characteristic of minimizing free energy
as a as a form of quantifiable
uncertainty so we'll touch back on that
again in a moment but the the the what
active inference provides is a kind of
normative holistic framework for what I
argue should be applied to agent based
modeling it it itself addresses agent
based modeling that phrase is used in
the textbook this is not a foreign you
know out of left field kind of invasion
of active inference and agent based
model and proposing there's so much
overlap and I think it's just an
underutilized connection that's already
been made right um active inference is
based in you know it it provides neural
process theories meaning that we're not
just you know assuming in the same way
with agent based modeling we might
assume oh all people are utility
maximizers um in this case we're not
just assuming it we're we're looking at
neuronal Dynamics we're looking at you
know Decades of research into using
neuroimaging studies and looking at how
you know how does the brain really
function how does it handle uncertainty
different kinds of Behavioral Studies
and tasks where you can you know record
uh MRI or EEG along the way and look at
the Dynamics of those um uh of that data
that's being collected along the way and
um and then from there we can start to
kind of model how that
works so um as I already mentioned uh
we're still looking at a kind of
belief-based framework which is to say
uh you know we're looking at uh for for
agents who have beliefs and they update
their beliefs and they do that by way of
the free energy principle which is
minimizing uncertainty uh we we start we
start to ex we start to see these
organisms that we're modeling humans or
otherwise we start to have naturally
emergent adaptive Behavior right by by
trying to figure out what's going on in
your environment and then adapting your
actions in order to better understand it
to better realize your own goals you're
effectively minimizing your uncertainty
and uh the free energy principle
basically is a kind of free energy is
like a proxy for that uncertainty that
that renders a lot of these things
computationally tractable meaning that
we're able to quantify it we're able to
report it whenever we run agent-based
modeling we're able to like actually
look on a chart and a graph how much
free energy is being reduced uh over
time you know and and look at the agent
internal beliefs about you know what
what is it that they're figuring out uh
within their environment over of course
is simulation um the view from from this
perspective is that uh another aspect I
I already addressed the expl exploration
exploitation balance and tradeoff uh
self- evidencing this means that agents
in order to minimize their uncertainty
um one way that they can do that is is
um to try and act to realize their goals
there's something they want something
that they expect right and so it's as if
you have this prior set of belas of what
you want to see in reality this is the
you know it's this is the kind of
framework that active inference deals
with but also referring back to you know
Juda Pearl as clippinger mentioned uh
you know this is a kind of basian idea
you know this is rooted in something
like like basy and uh statistics or even
mechanics where the idea is that you you
have your prior knowledge you bring it
to the situation and then that will
impact how you update your beliefs based
on new information right so we're we're
not always starting from some blank
State some some starting from scratch
we're always coming to a situation with
what we thought before and then that
gets updated how does that get updated
from active inference that standpoint
it's through free energy
principle um so you know it's I made
some points in this tutorial because I
realize we're we're we're really uh uh
you know I want to make sure we have
time to to kind of bring this back um
but uh with active inference that we
already have so many aspects of uh
reinforcement learning and active
inference which overlap we're trying to
create cognitive models you know active
inference I don't want to say it's
necessarily competing I don't know if
that's the right word but it's you know
it's it's it's making advances that
reinforcement learning is trying to make
itself so um and uh and with active
inference it's like well we with Act
inference we're actually basing this on
you know a variety of of of principles
you know
that again sorry zooming through you
know we're able to like cognitively
model you know what's what's going on in
the mind in various ways that
reinforcement learning is really lacking
um today it's it's really lacking that
it's it's uh you know these models are
being built to be highly performative
but they're missing the mark whenever it
comes to something like realism and
basing
uh basing these reinforcement learnings
and something like a you know science
that extends Beyond just the mathematics
of machine learning right we we want to
be able to find biological physiological
substrates for how all these things
happen right um we want to be able from
there to be able to apply everyday words
and interpretability so what is it that
defines what a habit is what what
process is involved whenever a goal is
formed and made and then from there uh
you know attempted to be achieved
through action uh you know what defines
planning what is
prediction um so I just want to see if
there's anything else I might be able to
touch on this was a nice um you know for
for for anyone and maybe I should have
started with this but this is a little
bit more of an intuitive glance and this
is actually these are not words from uh
Carl friston surprisingly uh they're
from uh Sarah Feldman Barrett who's at
Northeastern he uh you know nearly as
rep reputable as Carl friston in the
Neuroscience field and I just personally
uh as someone who's also interested in
in in neuroscience and cognition you
know I find her work fascinating she's
done a lot of work on um emotions and uh
you know kind of affective Neuroscience
so it has to do a lot with looking at
what's going on inside the mind of you
know especially humans and so this is
kind of trying to provide an intuitive
glance that you know how can we think
about B in Frameworks about um um
inference about active inference as well
so it's like uh this is a long quote
from a podcast that she did your brain
receives sense data from the world
sights and sounds smells and so on
receives sense data from the body so
when there's a loud bang or a tug in
your chest your brain receives that
information as the outcomes of some set
of causes but what caused that loud B
what caused that tug in your chest your
brain actually doesn't know it only
receives the outcomes it has to guess at
what the causes are this is called an
inverse problem you know what the
outcome is you don't know what the cause
is so your brain has one uh you know
another source of information available
to it that is past experience memory um
apologies for just like doing a
slideshow karaoke here but you can read
it for yourself I suppose but the point
is and with some of this highlighting
it's like we're actually taking account
of a variety of things you know we're
taking account of interoception meaning
observations that arise from within the
body or for an active inference agent uh
you know it it it it has to kind of
model itself you know I mentioned
earlier you know if I if I'm hungry this
goes beyond the five senses in that kind
of perspective right touch taste feel
all of that um with this it's like well
I need to understand what's going on
within my body I need to understand
what's going on outside of my body as
clippinger you know referred to earlier
the idea of a Markov blanket it's kind
of like I need to figure out what
defines the boundaries between myself
and what's around me you know on the one
hand I need to have a model of myself in
order to maintain it uh otherwise I
succumb to the environment around me to
use some of the language that's used in
uh you know the textbook it sounds a
little Bak but you know we're referring
to real world circumstances if I you
know if I don't take care of myself I
will naturally Decay like that is kind
of the sort of the principle the world
is entropy so to speak right it's like
if I don't eat food you know I I I fall
apart so I I need to have a model of
myself what's going on within I need to
have a sense of what's going on without
uh and then and then I need to be able
to kind of synchronize those things in
such a way that I can continue to exist
as an entity within this environment
around me that's a that's a that's a
very intuitive you know perhap perhaps
not very well technically described but
for now an intuitive sense of of kind of
what defines a markup blanket so you
know for this is a sort of foreshadowing
for tomorrow we'll talk about uh this
this really interesting project we're
working on for the biofirm uh with with
with uh you know Daniel and and and
under guidance of of John um you know in
that in that sense we're we're trying to
develop homeostatic agents uh
homeostatic meaning agents who you know
their own sense of their
survival is predicated on uh the the the
homeostasis that their environment
around them so we're trying to create
agents who
take care of and attend to the uh the
environment around them as if their own
Survival depended upon it you know this
is a very interesting kind of uh kind of
flip you know where where where you
actually want to match and model the
environment around you but also take
care of it in a way that you can
maintain it within those bounds just as
you know I have to eat in order to
maintain my energy levels you know that
the agents need to take care of their
environment you know within some kind of
range to where it has you know enough
caloric energy so to speak um so um I
think for now John is there anything
that you think I have not addressed that
might be useful to to our audience or if
anyone else would like me to touch on
anything maybe something I skipped or or
otherwise i''d be happy to to speak
more no I I think you you you you've uh
covered some of the really key points
that um that are that what I I think is
you've done is what differentiates
active inference from the more
traditional agent-based modeling I think
is important because when people think
about agent-based modeling they they
sort of default to what the traditional
models are and I think that you've done
an excellent job of sort of uh
highlighting what the difference is and
what the the the having having that
broader perspective that more grounded
interdisciplinary perspective you you're
able to more not only represent the
complexity of it but also provide a a
way of modeling agents in within that
complexity um and I think that the the
the the notion of a
the the homeostatic nature of of of an
agent trying to live in in conjunction
or really harmony with the world around
itself is depending upon its survival
and its ability to stay alive and
differentiate and have complexity but
the synony of the environment is really
another key point because I uh I think a
lot of people they think oh well you may
say like navigating a fitness landscape
you're just trying to optimize different
levels but in fact the landscape itself
is shaped you're doing joint Niche
construction so it's a much more complex
notion than
traditionally understood General
modeling and I think in in consideration
we looking at tomorrow this whole idea
of the btic character of model having it
based upon principles and biology and
nature and having being able to create
an economic agent that acts that way I
think is is is really quite important um
and so maybe some people have some
questions about that that that we want
to to focus on or not but that I I
that's something that that I think it's
important to highlight
yeah awesome presentation Andrew Ernesto
if you have a question also anyone in
the live chat is welcome to ask a
question no questions thank you very
much this is so
inspiring well and also just to to put
it in context I know this is something
that you're very interested in in this
whole idea of a btic and economic system
and been looking at this yourself so
this is really trying to lay down the
principles really the the scientific
principles and computational principes
of doing this and and and uh and we'll
get in more to that tomorrow but that
that's the the intent
here yeah a lot more to say again in our
remaining 40 minutes I'm happy to read
questions from the live chat I'm also
happy to screen share and look at some
of the
registered participants backgrounds and
interests sure okay okay you can unshare
Andrew and
I'll pull up some word
clouds all
right okay
okay
so let it
load okay these are word clouds that are
generated from the
participants registration
information and we'll we'll zoom in on
them and and uh I'll I'll just kind of
mention them and we'll we'll zoom in and
uh
if anyone has a remark or something that
they want to uh like highlight or call
out about it just go for it okay so this
is a word cloud of the uh 150 or 200
registered presenters overall asking
about what is
your personal background so the biggest
and and and the this is scaled just by
number of uses of each term so one
person mentioning a term a ton of times
might make it large so just to be taken
as sort of a representative we see those
tiny two letters AI which could mean
almost anything at this point and a lot
of other terms like computational
research systems
Neuroscience
cognitive philosophy social
academic robotics technology
practice this kind of speaks to the
broad range of topics that that that
leads people
into joining and at least entering that
information on the uh form any thoughts
on this or we'll keep on exploring these
word
clouds okay okay all right again just
just raise your hand or or or go for
it interest
okay well there's I'm interested the
notion of community and systems I mean
uh
applications the community seems very
strong yeah yeah and that that's the the
sensor of a of a later
one so here we asked what what would be
useful and by asking what would be
useful and what would be interesting we
alluded a little bit to the Dual
composition of the expected energy what
would be useful what would be utility
what would be pragmatic and then what
would be interesting what would be
epistemic so hearing what would be
useful you know here we are in in
applied active inference Symposium
wondering about how does active
inference go from being a unifying
framework for ecosystems of shared
intelligences and all these different
kinds of things that we've heard already
and we're going to hear in the Symposium
to come so interesting that
systems a way to
operationalize and really move forward
from framings of complex adaptive
systems to having the
implementations and also the community
and the people understanding research
models
collaborators and then a lot of
different topics that are being explored
in more mainstream computational science
Fields like multi- agent algorithms
Andrew alluded to that and kind of
brought that up in the context of the
the Goldilocks parameterization
question the agent based model can be so
simple it gives you a great intuition it
shows at a a demonstration layer how
simple Behavior can lead to complex
outputs on the other hand the agent base
modeling can go the other extreme where
it's so sophisticated then it loses its
transferability so that's what people
would find useful and then
here's what they put for what would they
would find
interesting
applications make sense as that's what
this Symposium is all about and again a
lot of other ideas thinking about
different specific systems research
ideas architectures synergies toolkits
insights
implementations
support Collective
directions here's
asking what would help you in your
learning and applying active inference
and community
looms
large other people as well as some of
the more tool resource textbook
education examples Frameworks
interactive
tutorials different languages
python what does anyone think about
this I'm uh a little surprised that we
not seen the phrase llm anywhere
um I just uh kind of noticed that so one
of the one of the points that that I you
know have been trying to work out and I
hope to speak more on tomorrow is um you
know integrating active inference with
llms and uh you know there have been
attempts to to do this and even even
with priston and Par and folks you know
that there there's been attempts at
trying to pull out an agent's beliefs
and then use an llm to process those
beliefs like kind of decode them and
re-encode them in natural language so to
speak it's as if the agent is speaking
and saying what it thinks and believes
and why it did what it did is you know
another layer of
interpretability and uh I don't know I'm
slightly surprised to not see llms
anymore um you know it maybe it's a
little too maybe that's a little too on
the frontier right now um I know it is
in many other areas you know and it's
um sorry in the couple minutes we have
it just uh you know something that I've
been working on personally and this is
feeding into the the biof firm is um how
how do we how do we use llms in a way
that we can actually integrate them with
you know all these major priorities that
we have uh where where we want to have
agents who actually have defined goals
right and and and ways of trying to stay
alive you know in a way that they
interact with their environment in a way
that it's as if their own Survival
depends upon it we don't want llms which
you know again I'm just saying this
quickly you know I don't me to sound
disparaging but llms in one sense can
act as like functionally as Talking
Heads where you just send in some text
and they try to predict what would be
the best text in response they still
subject to hallucination to confabulate
making things up so to speak even though
the answer looks structurally sound you
know and and and so the my point is that
rather than viewing llms as uh as agents
I don't I don't I don't think they are I
think that uh you could have an active
inference agent who is augmented with
the capacity for natural language by
having it interact with an LM right so
yeah sorry to so deep
my own yeah scan scanning across all the
registration fields for llm
mentions so how does active inference
apply to the design of llm
systems AI outside of llms better ways
of Designing internet skill protocols
and governance systems and should
converge with tiny ml to challenge llms
deep learning so it's it is interesting
that that it's uh referenced with only a
glancing
blow and and uh We've even seen earlier
like in the responses to similarities
and differences with reinforcement
learning with friston earlier about the
increased amount of attention and Tool
development and the later and more
professional maturity of training
environments and this is like one of the
key fosi for the open source active
inference ecos system and for the
Institute is to develop those kinds of
methods and trainings and all on
boardings all these different aspects of
of increasing the
professionalization so let's look at the
challenges so this was what what what
are the challenges facing
your learning and applying active
Influence People interesting the problem
problem and the solution models the m
math
software maths again mathematical
understanding difficult physics
scaling simple
examples you know it's it's it's
interesting um because in the larger
conversation about what AI is I mean
it's it's that that conversation is so
dominated by uh large language models
and quote generative models within large
language
models um and and what least I've been
observing I tried to refer to my my
initial slides is that they're starting
to appreciate the
limitations of of the large language
models moved towards more agentic models
and more towards causal models and hence
creating aent architectures that do work
with large language models but they're
still there's not they're still not
based upon biological principles that
we're discussing active inference there
more of the mechanical models being
applied over and I I think to me from
from a point of view of sort of the
um the sociology of science soci it
there there seems to be these different
worlds that that I mean the number of
people that i' I've known sort of in the
open AI well they're they're very
unaware of active Ence and some of the
critiques that are if you if you listen
to the Gary Marcus he's got a very
pointed critique of of um of of large
language models and not being able to
achieve abstractions but that doesn't
extend to appreciation appreciating what
the the opportunities are an active
inference and so there are there s of
these islands of understanding that they
still exists
um and I think that's one of the
challenges and when you talk about
developing an infrastructure I me you
need there's huge financial resources
are going into the the the large
language models
infrastructure and where I think that
the totally bias on this I think all the
the opportunity is totally within the
active INF of free energy principle and
I think that's where the science is
going and yet it's it's still it's sort
of in in this isolate World um and I
think the only way to get out of that is
start to to really start to showing the
applications and showing the with
results and and uh because uh but it
it's it's it's interesting I me to see
they're they're different they're
different worlds um um but I I think
that what's the there's a peing and so
the hype curve around uh uh the large
language models and and it's going to
they're going to descend my bet is
they're going to descend into a valley
of doubt and you suddenly you're going
to see that showing up and the in the
Nvidia stock going down and then people
are saying you can't you know destroy
all the natural resources on run these
models you don't have to you know the
other and Carl alluded to this in his
earlier comments today you know I mean
he was talking about climate change and
models compression I and I think that's
going to be a driver of this
um so but that that's some my my
observations on on these yeah these
clouds is yeah I'll bring in a question
from the live chat also welcome Ma just
thought I'd bring you on if you wanted
to participate in this panel or just
chill so Stephen selette wrote is the
lack of llms
mentions because large language models
are different to Dynamic agent belief
modeling
and you want to take that
you could you could you repeat that uh
yeah question is the lack of llms in the
word clouds here but just more more
generally thinking about similarities
and differences between active inference
generative models and llms is is that
because large language models are
different than Dynamic agent or belief
modeling I I don't want to approach this
this question in the in the wrong way
but
I I will say that that that as far as
you know whenever it comes to llms and
and dealing with you know they internal
parameters are obviously highly
quantitative and then they're dealing
with with natural language as to
and then switch back to looking at
active inference agents which you know
are highly quantitative in nature and uh
typically you know if you're making
continuous time models uh you're looking
at again quantitative information and
then even with discrete models you're
looking at you know these kind of
discrete values that you could
potentially move in the direction of
trying to you know make it I think this
has already been done uh but uh you know
there there are agents who um you know
have been used to try and understand
like oh we can read individual tokens
then move up to another layer and then
we have entire sentences and then move
up to another layer we have entire you
know paragraphs or ideas that kind of
thing is done but I think this kind of
like llm with
quantitative uh grounded agents like
that connection uh is still that in my
view that's kind of the frontier of
where things are at and so it's
difficult for people to conceive like
how can we how can we Translate encode
decode re-encode natural language in a
way that's readable by these
quantitatively oriented agents and then
vice versa how do we transition
quantitative beliefs into natural
language that's the very thing that I've
been uh you know looking at thinking
about uh recently I made like a active
inference like PDP agent who uh you know
they what they do is that they use their
beliefs about which action to take and
then that action that they carry out is
actually corresponding to a prompt to an
llm and you can actually take those
beliefs the quantitative beliefs find
some way of meaningfully interpreting
them and then putting that into these
blank spaces in the prompt is as if you
can have the agent say in real time I
currently believe this with probability
this give me you know a solution to this
problem you know based on so so being
able to find this kind of newer versus
the quantitative and the qualitative you
know it's it's historical problem when
working with with data that go back
centuries at this point so um it's it's
really exciting though it's really
exciting to think of how to bridge that
kind of Gap and I I still haven't seen
anyone you know nail that down this this
is the frontier this is where we're at
and I think that's kind of the next
thing for everyone to really be
considering thinking about working on um
and I'll give my view on how that could
be done
tomorrow
well um yeah I mean effectively llms
don't really encode explicit beliefs or
really maintain a persistent model of uh
the world um even when we sort of give
them a sort of loop by which we um
communicate with them that Loop in
itself doesn't actually factor into the
predictions that is going to do um so
they they just lack a framework for
recursively updating beliefs which is
probably why it's not being thought of
here um but also mainly that you know
llm agents are only agents by virtue of
sometimes being connected to stuff and
having um explicitly stated goal but I
don't think that actually qualifies them
to the
agents you know yeah I I totally concur
with that I from my perspective I I
think that the reason
that LMS are are are not looking at that
are are not looking at or that whole
mindset is not looking at at belief
structures in in subjective experience
is I think it's a product of a whole
sort of objectivist reductionist
methodology that um is has been tuned
not to look at agentic systems I mean in
my generation if if you if you were in
biology you and and you talked about
agentic systems you you were you were
outed I mean that was that that that was
verboten and I think the the there's a
whole school of thought there's a whole
set of of in aonian sense a normal
science built around uh a sort of
objectivist reductionist non- agentic
notion and and and uh and so there it's
a new generation that's coming in in
both in biology and in and modeling and
cognition there's recognizing this
notion of an agentic perspective of
beliefs and updates and and that's a
huge shift I think in in sort of the
epistemological perspective of of a lot
of what has been traditional
science that's really interesting
there's also just
operationally the difference between
taking a very large fixed number of
parameters in a given model 70 or 7 or
405 training on existing data and then
finding patterns or igen modes or
activation um summaries that have
secondary interpretability but there's
not really an effort of trying to find
interpretability at the level of
activation of a given neuron it's about
looking at patterns and trying to find
Collective level interpret abilities
like in in the AI interpretability field
contrast that with designing from the
ground up an example agents where the
beliefs are explicitly encoded
numerically and so that's a different
mode of building and also one that's
hinted at in in this 2023 paper with Ma
and others that highlights element of
explicit semantic interpretability and
also explicit semantic interpretability
of uncertainty estimates whereas a
string of tokens emitted by an llm that
says I'm not sure it's sure about saying
that but that doesn't mean that it has a
given
certainty about the
reference so understanding what the
communication semantics of llms are is
incredible and what they do and I think
when we look at this Cloud for people's
responses how can active inference make
a difference in 2025 where there there
is
llms
here many many kinds of systems and
that's sort of like a microcosm of what
the Symposium is different people with
different systems of
Interest asking H how do these
different attributes of the model that
we're talking about the first principles
grounding semantic
interpretability surprise and
uncertainty and its bounding as a
central component as opposed to reward
how do all those things really play
out what does that demonstration look
like in in different
systems h
here's go for
Andrew no I was just going to say on
that that that previous one you were
just looking at I I I really appreciate
that kind of a broad-mindedness that
that people seem to be exercising I like
seeing terms like uh symbology scientist
governance um
industry I mean those are some very
very excited to see people who who want
to you know so much work has been put
into kind of the theoretical and then
sort of like in in in vitro and and in
lab and and in simulation kind of work
that's been put into active inference so
I'm just really excited to see you know
with the the um
International the the conference the the
back of inference conference that was
given recently and being able to see
like a drone that's flying based upon
the free energy principle and things
like that I'm just really excited to see
more
kind of real world applications right
and and kind of uh creating uh you know
systems and and applications for like
real world use cases it's it's really
cool to see some of those terms
there yeah I think that's going to be
really critical so see
yeah here's the cloud for how are you
applying active inference again systems
I I think just reflecting people talking
about variety of different systems types
but and also reminding me of my own
journey to active inference being
excited about complex adaptive systems
however not really having a software
toolkit or a formal way to proceed past
okay we think about nested multi-agent
systems and then where's the software
toolkit and then we're right back to
where Andrew showed us on the slide it's
like well we can do a really simple one
in net logo or we can engage on this
Enterprise scale engineering research
program and yeah here's a more
incremental interoperable way to have
portfolios of motifs and generative
model components and be assembling and
scanning across these different kinds of
compositions like three ant nestmates in
the desert three ANTM nestmates in the
forest and these different kinds of
environments being able to compose them
and over the last several years seeing a
lot of the advances in the category
theory in the first principles physics
surrounding all these sort of research
things and it's like that's kind of the
water drawing out and then that's the
question about how it looks when it is
applied and that's what I guess we
convene around in this Symposium and and
are seeing differently in 2024 than in
previous
years that's curious so what what's the
change that you've seen in pre previous
years versus this year and then so
looking forward more of an
application Andrew or ma what what what
do
you think I was yeah
but absolutely that that that is I oh
yeah please yeah I mean I feel like um
the work of Maxwell ramstead C Casper HP
I mean obviously Carl but um a lot of
people who perhaps came from more
Dynamics uh decided to take a real
interest in what we could do with
something that was so scale-free and I
find that it's been really really rich
in terms of the different kind of
theories we've tried to sort of reforme
I know that's what most of my work is is
a Reformation of existing social
sciences um and to your point Daniel the
the problem we still have is that we're
missing like these key little plugs um
that yes you could couch as you know
just different schemes of message
passing but you still need some
interesting tools to to have a a very
good description of the vast vast
variety of types of structures that we
have Which social sciences have done a
really great job at if not intuiting at
least describing properly but we still
don't have the best tools to make
accurate predictions and that's part of
the reason why most of our polls when we
make them are are n they're useless and
that should be the main thing we apply
them to is just literally just
understanding where we're at not even
making predictions just understanding
where we're at and we still fail at that
so I'm very
I'm very encouraged by by seeing this
and I hope that we will start valuing
more and more interdisciplinary
perspectives that are sometimes more
technical but also sometimes uh you know
more philosophical or um or
social awesome also while we're in this
in in the coming workshops tomorrow will
be more of a Biore Regional biofirm
focus and then day three will be
entirely with
at all on this topic and and I want to
show one really operational open science
Crossover with llms and active inference
which is and I'll put it in the live
chat as well here I used
perplexity which does an internet search
summarizes and translates information
using llms so here we'll pick on Alexi
there's a a profile a learning plan and
a set of small medium and large project
proposals about active inference so this
is just summarizing expertise and
experience here we have a learning plan
it's just a starting position but this
brings a new low bar to the kinds of
resources that everyone can take on in
their learning and use as like a
syllabus or a
curriculum and even as an interactive to
you know it will not get bored with you
asking to explain Concepts again and
again or using different metaphors or
making it applicable making it like this
poetry format putting it in this
narrative context and so even asking how
do I start with this or can you help me
understand what I don't know that puts
such a
centrality and and highlights
metacognition in
learning and then the project proposals
each of them structured according to
essentially what a grant officer would
be looking for and what a what a project
manager would be thinking about in terms
of small medium and large projects so
this
unprecedented High throughput way to
fuse even scanty input from a
participant in a inclusive open science
setting into real projects that if
enough people think hey that looks kind
of interesting then we're well down the
road of actually making it happen using
different kinds of of funding which is
something Michael lennin mentioned a
little bit earlier so it's sort of like
we can get really detailed and Technical
and Architectural thinking and and and
finessing the differences between
reinforcement learning deep learning
active inference and we saw slides to
that like when Carl showed the action
perception Loop similarities and
differences okay active inference
doesn't have a reward function it's not
optimizing based upon this
trained auxillary reward concept it's
just doing something direct with
likelihoods like that is critical that
is what makes the active inference
generative models what they are but then
looking at something like this which
wasn't so accessible one to several
years
ago that just feels like opening up and
unleashing what people can do and about
using these as Tools in our
Niche
and I think it's a total open and
unknown what happens when you can get to
this
level of project and learning plan for
for an arbitrarily complex field
with the patience of an AI That's just
going to accept questions all day long
like that's almost the
bigger applications
question again just zooming out from how
the architectures and the parameters are
similar and different to how are we
going to do what is authentic and right
and best given the tools we have there's
a bigger picture Beyond just holding the
magnifying glass to different
computational
artifacts that's well said Daniel I
really agree it's
transformative if anyone has questions
in the chat or here or any other things
they want
to mention
yeah what's going to happen in the next
two sessions John or what would be your
goals or preferences for for this Arc of
the Symposium for you yeah so I I I
think is as Andrew alluded um this the
session tomorrow is going to be really
on the application of of uh of active
agents uh to a a design of a economic
agent new kind of firm biofirm that's
homeostatic um and the objective of that
is to develop a new kind of incentive
structures a point to Collective
action um that are based
upon mimetic principles that I think
we'll see address a lot of the issues
that people are having in the whole idea
of bi Regional Finance and how to deal
with climate change and how to create
those incentives so there one of the
things I'll kick off with I've been
talking to a number of people in the
whole fields of of um um regenerative
Finance bi where they go bofi um this it
ties into the work that was done in
Elanor ostrom's work on uh how common
pole resource how do you manage a common
pole resource how do you incentivize
people different scales I really think
that and what you identify so the
requirements that people are looking for
it in order to address these problems
the scale and I think what we're be
talking about is through the
implementation of active inference uh
principles into an economic agent that
it provides I think a a a reasonable way
of of addressing these issues um and
that um um and and so that's part of the
conversation that we want to have and
and and bring together these two these
two worlds um then the third session is
to really look at this um from a a
broader point of view is saying where is
this going and this are the people that
we have in the panels are very off very
much involved with Enterprises um
applying it to nonprofits to applying it
to S problems looking at what they can
do with llms currently and what the
certain current agentic architectures
are and what happens when when you s
what happens when you go to full
autonomy what does it mean to have
autonomy um in in a in a in a biological
sense something keeping alive and what
does it mean to build systems that have
autonomy this issue of autonomy is sort
of fundamental uh when when when people
think of of autonomous organiz
autonomous cars or decentralized
autonomous organizations or the whole
idea of U the Central Bank the the the
the the principles behind something like
a Bitcoin is is like oh that that that
is autonomous but is it really
autonomous what is this new notion of
autonomy if we base it on biological
principles
um and I I think that's that opens the
door to a very different set of
discussions than than we're currently
having and it also opens the door to new
Notions of governance and how we can
build governance in to maintain the
homeotic states um and Andrew is
alluding to that so I mean that that
that that that's where I become a an
optimist and I'm not an optimist around
the extension of llms and and open Ai
and the and the tech
the tech Giants but I am an optimist in
being able to apply these principles to
to some of the fundamental issues we
having around climate and social equity
and economic
equity awesome okay in the closing
minutes if anyone has lost comments and
David's question too if you want to
address it Andrew or anyone else any
thoughts about how we start to develop a
multiscale approach to ethics
um I want allow time for other people so
I'll briefly say uh so so tomorrow um
you know we'll we'll we'll present uh
various aspects of the biofirm there
will be a little bit of a Redux to some
of the things I went through today just
to kind of thread The Narrative um and
I'll kind of talk about you know
homoeconomicus and all these kinds of uh
assumptions about human behavior and
things like that but uh um I mean
multiscale governance I what we're
trying to do with our bio firm is to uh
you know and clippinger refer to um uh
Elanor ostrom's work on the commons and
so I I'm going to address that a little
bit too but the idea is to be able to
have a kind of like adaptable system of
multiple agents uh you know and so we
have a kind of small Society so to speak
and uh you know they're kind of
governing the commons around them and by
being able to have something like the
capacity for one shared goals uh and two
adaptive learning such that they can
actually adapt what they do and what
they believe and actions they carry out
have those be localized to the current
context which is an essential part of
ost's like work is like it's not so
simple to just give a singular top down
instruction that applies in all places I
mean to be able to have that kind of
adaptivity and awareness of the local um
you know while at the same time having
agents who are kind of synced up in
these various ways I think that's a one
way of trying to approach governance and
then from there you might be able to
have
kind of layered you know you could have
individual hubs you know and then you
could have some kind of like
interconnecting system between them that
that extends that to an even broader
scale of multiple hubs and interaction
between them so just some just some
breadcrumbs there um
thanks yeah Ma and then John with the
last word on this
session yeah so I mean the question of
Ethics is a bit it's obviously
complicated but the
the the key part about whether we
coordinate around multiscale goal
sharing Etc share potention that's
intrinsic to poweractive inference right
it just is the question that isn't going
to be solved is what is good uh because
you can always say well you know what is
good is good by virtue of being
contextually sort of stable but there
may be other ways to be stable or that
might prioritize other kind of
individuals or entities Etc so I don't
think we're going to solve that question
however what we can solve is the is the
global versus local coherence of certain
kinds of beliefs relative to what might
constitute goodness at given scales and
find where the friction points might
arise because this version of goodness
is incompatible with this version of
goodness and therefore Uh something's
going to give somewhere an error is
going to have to propagate so I think
that's going to be answered but the the
larger broader question you you'd have
to look into different schools of
thought around what constitutes uh good
because we don't necessarily want to go
towards um moral realism um because
there's a lot of things that are baked
into that uh but you might want to go
into the uh ethical implications of neom
materialism and how it it is about
interactions and locality and at that
point it becomes about how do certain
pockets of ethical framework sort of
form and allow to just coexist away from
other pockets and what happens when they
start interacting uh which again we may
be seeing right now in the US yes good
point John any last comments on the
session oh this is great um and I think
U we we now surfacing some of the issues
that are really important to to talk
about and and um I think Le least well
we're going to be presenting is is a is
a framework um that at least we can have
these discussions in a more rigorous way
and in testable way um and uh I think
that's part of the way of moving it
forward so yeah awesome thank you okay
we'll take a one minute break see you
soon okay thank
you
e e